All right we're here and build and we're going to talk a little bit about sample all, for example,
with the new
universal windows platform it seems like sample everywhere all the time.
...excited about it so let me talk a little bit about myself
...not very good design so we have some folks here with design
how do you get started with design example apps
across all of the devices that are available for windows including holland, for example.
So, when we first started working with windows...specifically on example...took a look
at to ecosystems every kind of had in place we have the windows phone tool set we have
the windows tools that we really can...evaluation of what was that experience
every really wanted to have across-the-board so we have to do
is level set we had we had to come up with a single set of controls they could scale
appropriately across all the range of devices and...experience that are users
one I cnn so let's introduce ourselves first who are you what you do
...microsoft ok I'm jeff arnold them design
lead in the windows design studio specifically on the development platform with
timid very here and also own parts of the shell as well so cartels
little about the design process with sam was different than designing other things you
...dev have to do it how do you think about all these things at once when you're doing design
share so the way we started is...we do work very closely
with example team on we took a look at the windows common controls and the windows phone
common controls from a design perspective and thought about how to converge them in a way that really
...the best of both worlds together and then we...closely with...engineering team?
...so when you say windows comp by the way you are I'm currently
...and I'm from the windows engineering team about with
...fantastic so when you talk about the column common controlling what are those
...is...collection of these things what are the yes there's,
there's quite a large collection of that...things like the context menu the date...
However,...and what do, you know, these things change based upon
...can you can use is their way to
build and app with design core that works across
all the devices or do you have to have a core and then sort of a design perspective?
...it's really up to...how they want to handle...
the controls are built to work with all the input devices that we have today with mouse with touch with
keyboard...even comptroller for xbox and,
then like it's really down to the developer do they want to creating more
tailored experience for specific device like a phone how they would handle that differently than they would
...for desktop so as I as I've started dabble example I've
done some wpf stuff if you're a wpf developer moving over to sort of
across platform maybe this is for the technical forms
...the crossed windows platform thing is they're going to be a job
...going to be some kind of scenes in the way you do things please introduce yourselves and tell us maybe
...for that I'm putting me I work with...the example ...example team.
...I'm team you rm also a program manager
...so how do you move from like your wpf
app let's say I have a really good...app and I want to move into like
a universal windows platform I think did the good thing about,
you know, if you have the skills and...xhtml...talk we throw the turnarounds
animal quite a bit xhtml first and foremost as a language and, wpf...has
and implementation of that language and windows runtime has implementation of that language so for the most part, you know, if you
...vpf developer you already knows...windows platform developer as well
...just becomes kind of the nuances of what are the common controls that are available
wpf has a different set not really a...about the core things like carmine mention
...pickers and inputs and buttons and things like that those are all pretty standard and, then, you know, there's,
there's a big ecosystem available for jpf and,
those things probably won't directly translate over for
universal windows apps definitely there...wouldn't because the implementations are a little different but,
if you if you have the skills of...developer than.
There I'd say the jumpers really only in understanding the windows runtime not necessarilythe
ui language or anything like that I see so what actually...out even as a
...developer you actually probably have a step up in understanding universal
windows apps because you already have to think about windows size changes and things like that
we're now asking developers to be aware so what this...project what would say
want to build a project that will target my phone.
Desktop and then...what would that project looks like services
...so right now right after that if you just
...windows app at that point that app is going to work across all of these devices right...the
...you don't have to anything specific if you don't want to all you have to do is, you know, create a single app and it
already has the capability run across all of these different device families if you do want to tailor
rbi...recommendation...just think about like windows size and capabilities most
should meet enough for you to think about in terms of...the device characteristics and, you know,
most likely this thinking about your you why in terms of effective pixels to get
you far enough out there and then if you want to for...are there are other api
...that you can use and all that stuff and but all of this is going to be contained inside a single project if you want
...so you pretty much started thing and it works.
But, it might not look very good on the phone...my look really good on the desktop and
...do create a new project that builds on top of that core.
That...the old way of doing things you don't need to
create new projects you just need to create a multiple representations of your you
...for you, for example, when you say phone I would ask what exactly about the phone are
you looking for example, if you are looking for you know, tailoring your ui for one hundred use
would suggest that you think about okay what is the...that's driving it
it's maybe it's about the diagonal size of the device because it's about...
the devices one hand and using it so if you're thinking about it in terms of that then you could probably look for
...that gives you the...container you why these on that I see that makes
sense so I'm a horrible designer so I'm larger how does sample help you
...a good designer and then the second and more important question is how do I get a good
sense of designed for these particular types of devices?
...I can start...so there's a concept in this...
there's a design guideline that we talk about...break points and break points is screen
wits in these effective pixels when app has an opportunity for...layouts so,
for example, on a phone makes no sense to have a one...layout but as
...goes to run on a tablet or laptop moving two-a-two
...layout when there's more effective pixels...can make sense
so a real-world example here is a mail application running on the phone.
Could have a message list and then when it runs on a tablet...message listen
...previewing also as a screen gets bigger and you pay attention to these break points that we have guidelines
find...really tailing so where are these guidelines...you have guidelines where are they
...look at the...so there's...the windows ten...is available at design that windows dot com
...released today so there's a ton of information about
their out there there's code samples case studies tons of information how does
...help us at design-time sort of take into account these things
do have to make one sample page for the phone
...one sample page for the actual two-column layout...you do it
...so...built...comic controls the you kinda get what...we say is like the
default of windows just out-of-the-box you drag-and-drop any other controls on
the page like the pivot control it works inside...that three hundred-twenty pixel space as the
...as advice size gets larger it takes up the space appropriately for that device
size spices and you know, and, it's not actually...like to me I don't feel like it's a function of
like how to make it more beautiful from...device...disjoint...is going to look
...shows devices becomes more of a function of is the functionality
there appropriate to that devices I
have more space I might as well use it for clickable stuff right
...taking advantage of screen real-estate is definitely one of those things I think it's
...of something that we have not done negative job
...prior on somebody's larger screen devices really...advantage
of the extra real-estate...you know, leaving space for more content but then like,
you know, just other things you can take advantage of on like on a phone
...gps and stuff like you may actually just have different features...you want to add into your application
just because it's on the phone as well so I'm kind...new but this?
Is there is there a way in the example page to say do this?
If we're in a wider screen or...view because the way I think about is I think about html
and examples like way you could
...more things with that but html you...specify view poured size for...their way to do that
example with your designing stuff so that's kind of order question...or
There's a session right now going...cygnus connecting the session
...document about that and I have a session tomorrow...be doing a deep dive on some of these concepts of
...so example yes we have introduced some influence...state manager
where you can now create inline in markup just a simple rules engine by using some of our new
api like...just specified...when the current window...is anything
...equal to a specific...pixels you can just have...have a single-line and
mark-up and that pretty much was stable automatically get applied pissing
...so what is what is your guys's prescription for building
...are like a free-market should use I've heard of ibm is that something that
were prescribing that you should use...you're...these kind of applications of so why is that the best
...I think the you know, to me and...is a tool just like any other tool...somebody's
toolbox I don't think that you'll hear from our team specifically say this is the best way to build
and app apps come in many different shapes and sizes
in your needs a lot of people say ibm...the best way to test and
...some people don't care about testing unfortunately so...if you're building a game
...medium the best way to use a game...are all just tools that you should evaluate like what is best for your
app same thing even just on the controls and things, you know, ...the guidelines we mention to these are all
just guidelines and information available to you to make the best decision we want we as
windows one apps to be the best apps for that brand for that company for that,
you know, whatever...tool or thing that it's going to do for the
can the customer want to be best for those scenarios you know,
my mother-in-law doesn't care that was built using and bbn she just wants to be
fasten responsive and do exactly what she expected to do so, you know,
from an engineering standpoint yeah, there are some things that there are some benefits
and downsides to certain patterns and nmda certainly one of them you know,
...did thing you see a lot of the tools is kind of the standard code behind approach which
works for quite a bit of apps as well our platform is kind of agnostic to any of these patterns
like we welcome anything we've done, you know, some of the new things that we're doing
...actually you can do today and write code to do that but we have heard that
people, you know,...a very productive language and
people want that productivity in visual studio and using the binding engines and things like that so we've
...more these api is to be able to use more
mark-up in a more performance way as well that's awesome so what moving on
...to...what are some of the new things coming out,
for example, is there anything knew that we should know about...you...
You yes we have we have a set of new controls
...of be more building blocks to some of the app patterns so, we have
...couple new in I would I would say there's a lot of there's a lot of new as well as we talked about
kind of converging the designs across the windows phone platform and windows platform
...there's some new visuals the api...change which is good for developers with new
...have been refreshed...pickers one that comes to mind
looks a little different if you kind of compare the different platforms their we do have a new control
split you that kind of helps with kind of to a pain and, you know, the secondary
type content information that helps with the some patterns rainy alluded to some of the more framework
features...around responsive design and things like that
and then we did this year we did a bunch of performance work so, we've introduced a new a new way to do
binding that gives again retains the same productivity for the
developers but achieves...performance in all...in
...and that was really actually influenced by at the office team who uses
ample to build their...universal apps and they have
...start out with this their own version of a binding engine and heavily, heavily influenced
the feature that we but superbowl so you said something...patterns what is an app...what ways?
So, the app patterns are we first started looking at what how we wanted to put together
applications and when inside of windows ten which we took an audit of all the different
navigational patterns that are out there today across all platforms and, what we came up with
...we had things on windows phone like inhibits and, you know, hop
and those things I types of things we've kind of have an...come up with a ways of actually bringing you know,
things like hamburger patter now to windows...ways of building and some of these patterns
are is very prominent very much out there in...the world that people use on a daily basis
so you sort of made common controls of those patterns that some of them are common controls
in some of them are building blocks to build the pattern themselves the...talked about the split
view that one was specifically built ...to enabled the hamburger pattern, you know,
the three bars the top left corner of the page we made up...specifically to make it easier
reporting of apps to windows that are already using...you have a
if you have a team that they don't have a designer they don't have...money to go and redesign entire
...just, come on, to windows they don't have to...this brake straight across because now we support that
pattern I see so I'm kind of a visual
learner like I have a hard time coming up with something new but once
I see it like I should use that kind of pattern do we have any
advice on how we should layout these things anywhere, yeah, so,
we know the every...has three main areas there's a there's navigational element how you navigate around
...there's a content area and then there's the commanding what you do on...content and like jeff was saying
with these...patterns we've taken all three of those elements and
kind of shown with each pattern what those could look like...should you place the command
...when you're on a found what should be at the bottom for one...navigation be well if it's a very important aspect of your
...should be on-screen should be viewable it should be accessible so
there is a lot of guidelines around those particular three areas of navigation
content and commanding as it relates to the app patterns to help people concerning that's awesome so,
not only always supporting people with here's some app patterns we're doing tools to sort
of realizes...actually what else can you guys tell us about...that you really?
The one thing that...talking about was...for that-you forgot now
...okay it's new layout...the of introduce example so,
previously used to have grid and stockpiles to kind of...uri and one of the things of
introduces a constraint-based layout...help you in the...some of these...patterns where, you
know, you want to morph you why based on available space a little bit of such that maybe some
...position and some place and you want more
...different place is going to be much easier...that using...paddle with
...which says this element has to be write-off this element instead of the
...something like that that's interesting is that this of new layout
...okay excellent any other any other newer exciting
...like to talk about yeah, I think it across-the-board in the thing for
...example team this year was a lot about enabling our first
...customers ...windows...there's quite a bit of a example use in an
core experiences of windows that put some new constraints on our team to be able to,
you know, be...of a windows user that when you click the start button and, you know,
it shows up in a certain amount of time in those things so we put a lot of focus on
performance and being able to achieve those course...
think about someone like office or windows itself using the same framework that we ask our customers to use you know,
that I can't think of a better case study than that so we you
know, we spent a lot of time...focusing on the performance and we start a lot of work to do
that I think that was probably one of our greatest achievements...and all of that a...
is not just for people who are ...within windows most of...laps or cplus-plus but,
all of the benefits that we did in the framework benefit anyone who's...the framework so
...reduction in memory benefits this simplest hello world app and,
those things and you don't have to be a customer like office or
...start menu to be able to get the benefits of all the things that we deliver
how you mention that the office team is using this up is there any other dog
...going on that inspired some of the stuff that
you've been having this start menu has the some?
Some animations that inspections...has
...a requirements to do some animations that enabled us or...
informed as...said basically say we got...support these things that they want to do so we implemented
...api transform three-d...capabilities within in
the framework to do a little bit beyond that perspective tutti that we have so,
you'll start seeing that up here and some of the windows builds on places like starred in some of the other apps for so
...you why for actual windows ten is built
...examine...a lot of the modern moi that's like the ultimate test there right,
yeah, that's pretty...thanks so much for coming by any
party words where should we go to look to find more I think we have so, we're all the
sessions are recorded we have a lot of good sessions that talk about the design perspective for windows
...carmine...had their session as well as I believe there's a panel that talks about with the with
...and those guys are going to talk about the windows story which doesn't have to be our customers story
...just a sharing our story and,
then likewise, you know, ...also have a lot of samples that are...though...of the universal
that's cool well this is very helpful I'm glad we because,
you know, as developers the battleship gray with our standard for so long we just can't afford it I'm glad we have
...design and from the technical site thanks so much for spending time with us where
can they look you guys up if they want to get a hold our audience...
...the social...us to give a...
People...him and he'll let me moi.
People to the active on the...you want them to discuss...on that have...odep that windows
...thanks so much for spending some time with
us we will be back if you have any other questions please
...to oxygen will related to everybody else thanks-a-lot having and we will see you.